[SPEAKER_03]: I thought of talking about ānāpānasati, but not... not like in terms of the technicalities of the sutta, more like just individually, but what people do when it comes to doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because obviously, you know, that sutta, like all the other suttas, it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: Due to its own kind of form and the way it's preserved, all you get is these outlines of the condensed statements that mean a lot more than what's expressed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is why, obviously, that whole sutta has been used to justify any meditation technique or practice you can come up with.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because even the things that the sutta does describe, they're not really instructions
[SPEAKER_03]: of a specific nature, they're more like results that you practice the words.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it says, like, breathing in you gladdens the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not something you can just do immediately.
[SPEAKER_03]: You read it, you immediately know what it is, and you immediately do it rightly.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Knowingly breathing in, breathing out, in the way the sutta starts, again, what what what is the knowledge of the breath?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it sensation in your nostrils?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is that how you know you're breathing?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you realize every line, every
[SPEAKER_03]: Every step, quote-unquote, it's not really a step, it's more like something to work towards, without telling you in more detail how you work towards it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to infer that yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, putting aside
[SPEAKER_03]: Those steps, in that sense, not regarding them as such, but actually just if you think for yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, what we do know, it's... say somebody, just as I said, anybody comes to read the suttas impartially, not arriving through the meditation method or through this or that, but just reading what the sutta says to the extent that it says it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It says that it leads to fulfillment of the four foundations of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the culmination of ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the mindness of the body, the feeling, the mind, and the images, the dhammas.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we know that much.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how would you now, in reference to that, describe your practice of non-forgetfulness of breathing?
[SPEAKER_03]: And what would be the value of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And what are the aspects of it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Characteristics?
[SPEAKER_03]: Things that are not clear, things that are clear.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, we talked about it differently in different talks and stuff, but forget about all that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's try and be neutral.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you know if you're breathing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only way I can say it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you need to stop doing whatever you were doing in order to find out that you are breathing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not in the sense of I need to stop it in order to then, you know, do something else and find out that you're breathing, but you might kind of have to stop it to the extent that if something is like completely, you know, your mind is completely distracted and you're completely absorbed in whatever you're doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need to unabsorb yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to unabsorb yourself a bit, because you might actually be kind of forgetting about
[SPEAKER_00]: You're breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: By doing lots of other things on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, does that mean you don't need to concentrate in order to know that you're breathing?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, as in, yes, it does mean that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It does mean that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it means that you need to un-concentrate from being too focused in order to know that you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why then people practice in concentration through their breathing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is the entire Theravāda practicing concentration through the sensations of the nostrils, of the breathing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... Basically, I would say, like, because the views, such as they are, misguided or whatever, as you might say that they are,
[SPEAKER_00]: We are generally all kind of based on this general notion that's taken for granted that meditation, in as much as any other kind of task that you might undertake to achieve something, is something that you have to be actively doing in order to get certain result from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you simplify that?
[SPEAKER_00]: People think that you have to be doing the meditation.
[SPEAKER_03]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's easier.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the basic, initial, yet fundamental overlooking.
[SPEAKER_03]: The knowledge of the breath does not require your concentration.
[SPEAKER_03]: The knowledge does not require concentration, even in worldly terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we ask, how do you know you're breathing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: What else can be said about it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where did you find that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where did you find that breath?
[SPEAKER_01]: Generally, peripherally, to whatever your technique...
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to go into peripheral to see it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good to see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Over there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is here?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is the breath?
[SPEAKER_02]: The body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Internal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Body is breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you breathe instead of the body?
No.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's... it's not necessarily clear, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can breathe, but you are not doing the breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your body has to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's always bound with the body, inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how you do... how you, or rather, what is your role in it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there a room for you there?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, if you if you see that it's the body breathing, then there isn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then there isn't, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the other aspect now, that can be uncovered, well, that can be covered up by saying, okay, so is the body always breathing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Does that mean you have no say in it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, because there are things that you just sort of can
[SPEAKER_00]: Feel like the heartbeat, for example, that is the body, the heart is doing it, and that you truly have no say in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't make any difference what you think or what you intend.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the breath is always intentional.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, it's your intention for body to breathe.
[SPEAKER_03]: So why is that important?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why can't you just say it's my intention to breathe?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is it just the body's breathing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why do you need to include both?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's kind of where the
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a... there's a blurring of boundaries there.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in the... that your intention kind of goes into the body and makes it breathe.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same way as, like, with... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And whenever there is blurring of the boundaries between the aggregates, there is ownership, there is conceiving, there is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's how you would be developing the satipaṭṭhāna of the body to its fulfillment, each through not blurring the boundaries of the extent of the bodily breath.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it does not mean overlooking the intentional aspect of it that does not pertain to the body, that's not bodily.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, anyway, it's not making the body do something, you know, but make it do something or become something other than what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of revealing what is the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's revealing what's already inseparable, an inseparable activity of the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, and again, that the same principle of you having an intentional input
[SPEAKER_03]: In the breathing, but not being able to not make it bodily or make it yours, it's your whole relationship with the entire body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Moving your arms, legs, head, eating, sleeping, it's exactly, it shares the same nature.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are doing those things, because the body can do those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you don't see that separation, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you are very much gripped with the desire and ownership of doing or avoiding those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: While they truly always remained on the domain of the body and physical.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what else then?
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, before we started this, we should have said, if you were to... well, if you were to practice mindfulness of breathing, what expectations do you have?
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you expect to come out of... out of that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's probably... what will I talk... talk myself, but... Do you have any expectations?
[SPEAKER_03]: If you sit down and say, okay, I'll sit down now.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've finished all the work, all the duties.
[SPEAKER_03]: Things are quiet.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mind is relatively free from hindrances, as far as I can see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And let me practice ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you have implicit expectations for something to come out of that practice?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or you're doing it for its own sake?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's actually something... something I was thinking about, kind of in relation to that subject as well, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Ānāpānasati in particular, or any, you know, specific...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, sit down and do this thing, it feels like it almost must carry some expectation with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you kind of catch your mind and say, okay, I'm having a sort of an expectation from it, and I would catch that and kind of withdraw from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the other kind of thing that would come with that is like, well, then what's the point of doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it feels like it should, you know, well, it's kind of this artificial thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: But so, is that expectation... Would you have such expectations if you're doing satipaṭṭhānas?
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're mindful of your body posture, would you have same expectations as if you were doing ānāpānasati?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's the same practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was what I then thought, that it's like... Actually, it's you who make it into something that, you know, is a specific practice that carries expectations.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I think it's probably because, you know, how we all arrived at this, from one angle or the other, with the ideas of... well, misconceived ideas of meditation being state of heightened
[SPEAKER_03]: Consciousness through a concentration releases in novelty experiences and self-hypnotic trances.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, ānāpānasati was always mentioned in those, you know, and you have all those other yogic practices of breath and visualizations and tantras and energies and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's kind of hard to just sit down and breathe without the implicit, yeah, but also what is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: What should happen here now?
[SPEAKER_03]: But, as I said, according to the suttas, it's the practice of satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the practice that brings the four foundations of mindfulness to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why don't you then have the same ecstatic expectations about sitting, standing, walking, lying down, feeling pleasant, unpleasant, neutral, seeing mind as elevated, depressed,
[SPEAKER_03]: Expanded, shrunk, light, heavy, thinking impermanence, four noble truths, but it's samvādha.
[SPEAKER_03]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you should.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, then, you should re-evaluate your expectations of ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it outlines the domain of the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mindfulness of the breath, non-forgetfulness of the breath.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how else, what else can be said in your own words, in terms of how do you practice non-forgetfulness of the breathing?
[SPEAKER_03]: How would you do it, for example?
[SPEAKER_03]: Come and ask you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, don't tell me any contemporary meditation technique, nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just tell me, how do I develop non-forgetfulness of my own breath?
[SPEAKER_03]: What would you describe to me?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's the perception, there's that direction, but there's also...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know what that means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: I understand.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just want to know how do I not forget about my breathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your grandmother is asking you.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: What do I do, son?
[SPEAKER_03]: You're going about your day.
[SPEAKER_03]: I go about my day.
[SPEAKER_03]: And while you're going... What would you recommend to me, then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you breathing?
[SPEAKER_01]: While you go... Are you breathing right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I am.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I forget.
[SPEAKER_03]: I keep forgetting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I not forget it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I carry on about my day in the way as before?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Really?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it depends on...
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends on what am I doing throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you would want to say, okay, so, if your actions are too distracting, you do need to, well, reduce the amount of your involvement with them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you cannot possibly...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not about attending to your breath, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to attend to it to know that you're breathing, but you certainly cannot be attending to something else fully immersed in it, as you just said, and expect to not.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, a degree of that peripheral recognition that you are breathing, here and now, this body is doing the breathing, needs to be allowed for.
[SPEAKER_03]: The space for that needs to be allowed for.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that the task that you're doing can't be requiring too much of your attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, that depends on the person, how much.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like a blanket formula.
[SPEAKER_03]: But say, okay, I still find that even hard.
[SPEAKER_03]: I minimize the tasks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I just sit down, maybe, and then do that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Non-forgetfulness of breathing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Should I sit down and try and do it in that more still manner?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or should I just not sit down and continue?
[SPEAKER_03]: Moving about and try not to forget about my breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's another trick question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I mean, you should.
[SPEAKER_03]: You should.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what the instruction says itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, yeah, you will be forgetting about breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then including that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then not... when you forget about your breathing, and then when you... when you're aware that you forgot about your breathing, you don't then run back, fully attending to the sensations of your breath, in order to remember it, because it's unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just need to remember that you forgot about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when you do, you see the breathing there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, knowingly you breathe in, knowingly you breathe out.
[SPEAKER_03]: The degree of that knowledge can change.
[SPEAKER_03]: It does not need to always be in front of your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, it's the training in yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's training in seeing the origin, or truth to the origin, or the source, or the womb of whatever's in front of you being attended, where your attention rests.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the breathing becomes a reference point for that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Man, it's particularly... well, I shouldn't say...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why is it particularly useful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought it was a battery warning or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's neutral, yes, but why couldn't you just carry on watching your full body postures?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there's intention involved.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's intention involved, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it does highlight that whole aspect of intentional involvement.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which can then, hopefully, as we said in the beginning, clarify, outline the extent of the physicality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, often, by overlooking your intentions, you kind of place yourself in that body, take the ownership of that breath.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, yes, you do have control, degree of control over it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that still does not take it out of the physical domain into the domain of your intention and your ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's hammering in that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Kind of basic recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what else can come out of mindfulness of breath?
[SPEAKER_01]: The four great elements would be one example of when you're saying about how the, yeah, the overlap doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, yeah, the four great elements that are completely outside of my control.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so then the nature of your control being completely secondary to the things you're controlling, your sense of control being completely enclosed within that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, that's something people can understand intellectually and drag their head around, but
[SPEAKER_03]: There are layers to that and there are levels that that thing needs to sink in.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what else?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't have mystical ecstatic expectations of your ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just knowing the breathing through practicing non-forgetfulness of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: In a controlled environment, not in the middle of a busy bus stop or something, although you could, if you're doing it rightly, what else?
[SPEAKER_03]: What else would be the benefit of that?
[SPEAKER_03]: What else would be the benefit of practicing
[SPEAKER_03]: The discernment of your intentional involvement with the physical breath, without taking it up, is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the mind becoming kind of withdrawn from...
[SPEAKER_03]: The animal calming down.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was... yeah, I was...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that's what I was going to say initially, but then, the way you asked me, it sounds more...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I was just going to say the mind becomes calm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because...
[SPEAKER_00]: But will the mind always become found?
[SPEAKER_03]: Could it become depressed as it is out there?
[SPEAKER_00]: I wouldn't say...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sluggish?
[SPEAKER_03]: Slow?
[SPEAKER_03]: Tired?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sleepy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there might be that, but not as a result of doing ānāpānasati rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I guess those things would come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's one thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are doing it rightly, but the mind is still...
[SPEAKER_03]: The mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not like you only observe the happy elated mind in the practice of satipaṭṭhāna of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, you see it as depressed, which means you might well be depressed, because it doesn't want to be sitting and recollecting the breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, especially when you took the the the transextatic astral projection element out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because you're depressed doesn't mean you're doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
Good news.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that is the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is the drilling.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is the training.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is the work.
[SPEAKER_03]: The training.
[SPEAKER_03]: He trains himself thus.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's doing it regardless of how he feels.
[SPEAKER_03]: And regardless of what his wrong views might still be expecting to come out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that doesn't mean he's doing it mechanically either.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because how can you mechanically be intending to not forget
[SPEAKER_03]: Good luck.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you start doing it mechanically, you won't be on the level of the knowledge of the breath.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know that the body is breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to concentrate on your nostrils to find it out.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to feel the movements in your belly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know the breath is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: In as much, you know you're seated, or standing, or walking, or lying down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yes, it would calm... well, it would calm the intentional involvement with the mental activity, with the activity of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mind still might be elated or depressed, but your intentional involvement, on account of the mood that that mind is in, well, that will lessen.
[SPEAKER_03]: That will be... that will subside.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, you know, it's the mind that presents you.
[SPEAKER_03]: It wants you to think about this or that, and pressures you towards it, but it's you giving in to it, and then self-fueling the vicious cycles of just revolving out of things that make you angry, because of which you revolve around them, because of which they make you more angry, and so on, more lustful.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if you were to refer back to the satipaṭṭhāna of the body, through the knowledge of it,
[SPEAKER_03]: Not through the misconceived observation of your sensations, through the knowledge of it, you are moving your intentional involvement elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's all that the mind is somehow pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now you can see, ah, there is the experience of the pressuring mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you create space between the two, between you and the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it does sound, in suttas, and it's actually even compared to the wheel-turner, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: The wheel-turner?
[SPEAKER_00]: I was going to mention that simile as well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it sounds like a, okay, no, I'm going to do this task now.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I shall go and I shall be planing some wood.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't have time now to indulge the whims of my mind that wants me to think about this and that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe I'll do it later, maybe I won't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, I'm just gonna sit and do this task.
[SPEAKER_03]: And to the extent I do it, to that extent I'll know I'm doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it kind of provides an indirect reference for whatever you're being pressured by.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're not doing it to get rid of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not doing it to get a mystical experience as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're doing it simply to hammer it in.
[SPEAKER_03]: The fact that the body comes first, the bodily activity comes first, the bodily domain comes first, and you're fully enclosed within it.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no outside of that, despite what your mind tries to make you believe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And would you say that's another way of... or another benefit, or another way of expressing the benefit, is that it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Revealing a level of activity that you're doing, that's going on, and that's not requiring any
[SPEAKER_00]: It's passion, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that never is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's always...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's below your passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's below the threshold.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's below the threshold of your passionate projects.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as much as then, like, you can say, well, like, whether you want it or not, like, the eyes are always seeing things, the ears are always hearing things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, they're on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just there, but then there's this
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you kind of go this extra step of like seeking out particular things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: So the thing is... learn to operate.
[SPEAKER_03]: The passion is real.
[SPEAKER_03]: The experience of passion is real.
[SPEAKER_03]: The experience of real will is real.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not about denying it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's not even about... well, you won't be able to prevent it, to make it... just tell it to stop coming.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because they're the result of a mind that's not awakened.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's still not free from ignorance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means, whether you wish or not to stop the passion or your will, it makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: It won't stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can only undermine it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you undermine it, as we say many times, first by not acting out of it, by containing it, by purifying your mind in that regard, but in this particular context of this practice of satipaṭṭhāna in general and ānāpānasati, well, you undermine it.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, there is a mind of passion.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there is pressuring thoughts, passionate thoughts, that mind wants you to think.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, I can be focusing my breath in really narrowing down concentration, so I stop thinking about this mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, no, you're just acting out of oppression.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're trying to make it go away, because it bothers me so much.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are not certainly uprooting it, and let alone understanding it.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, you don't want to get rid of it, you want to contain it.
[SPEAKER_03]: When I talk about enduring things on the right level,
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why I refer to it as, like, patience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because patience contains things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you already contain it through not acting out, but now you can contain it even more.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you say you have a mind of passion, pressuring thoughts, of passion, or real will, or whatever hindrance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Within that, there is a knowledge of breathing, on that physical domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter how big their passion or anger gets, how strong their pressure increases.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can never come over the underlying physical domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can never spill outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even if you act out of it, it's actually not spilling outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's your own ignorance perturbing the order of the picture.
[SPEAKER_03]: But fundamentally, the physical domain
[SPEAKER_03]: The domain of the senses, the domain of the knowledge of that breath inseparable from the body, it's always underneath the threshold of your intentional involvement with passion, ill-will, distraction, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by discerning that, by cultivating that, by training yourself in it, you are training yourself in the right order.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you don't think about the right order or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are putting your passion second.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not trying to get rid of it blindly, through ill will, through denial, through more craving against it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're containing it, exactly how you would contain the fire, until it runs out of oxygen.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it will run out of oxygen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because oxygen comes from outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: But there is no outside to this.
[SPEAKER_03]: It cannot persist.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, exactly, you got rid of it, just in the right way, without you needing to claim against it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's, you know, I was saying that in other talks a long time ago, you know, you can have your mind preoccupied with stuff, ideas and so on, but you can always discern peripherally that you just, in the midst of that, like, deeply engaging
[SPEAKER_03]: Passionate involvement of your mental level, you find your body just there, scratching, oozing, sitting, breathing, this... this thing, this creature, oblivious to all your worries and projects and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just... just there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you overlook it, then you ignore it, and then you continue to prioritize your intentional level, of your engagements, of your spilling out, of your acting out.
[SPEAKER_03]: And why is that possible?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you haven't trained yourself sufficiently enough in the right order.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you do, then even if you don't wish and want for the body to contain the passionate projects, it will.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's the order of things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you don't wish, oh, you know, may I stop regarding this mind, this mind, stop identifying with it,
[SPEAKER_03]: Stop suffering and bring pressure on account of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you will stop, because you're containing it and you're removing the fuel for its wilderness, for its passion.
[SPEAKER_03]: That fuel being nothing other than that wrong order, that it was the source of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Overstepping, misconceiving,
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the practice of mindfulness of breathing, the practice of non-forgetfulness of the breath, is the practice of yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not directly attending to your breathing, but discerning that you already know you're breathing, even if you don't attend to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the key.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what would you do if you get too involved with your breath?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'd do the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_02]: You would be outlining that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Involvement, again, you would outline your body.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, but what I mean, if you get too involved with your breath, say, you are recollecting the knowledge of breathing correctly, but now you're feeling your lungs and energies and just overly attentive to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you have to basically just do the same like what you just said, in regard to any passionate intention or any... Well, you might not be passionate, but say you are overly focused on your breathing now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it is a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Go on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, you don't have to stop breathing in order to resolve the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the problem is not that, like, you're breathing too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is that you are, like, becoming overly involved, as you said, by either, like, I will try and do it like this, I will try and focus it on like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see, you can discern there's a difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't need to
[SPEAKER_00]: Do all of that in order to breathe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're already breathing, like, normally, before you then start.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we covered all that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you do, but you do find yourself too focused.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you stop there?
[SPEAKER_01]: The feeling is the counterpart to that becoming too absorbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a... to see
[SPEAKER_01]: That pressure, then, I would say, feeling becomes more relevant as a way to... Well, you just keep it within the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not complicated.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, it might work, what you're saying, but you're knowing you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: The next thing you know, you're just feeling the breath too much.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all you think about.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're focused on it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Remember what?
[SPEAKER_03]: The breath.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you stop overdoing it, in the same sense, you stop underdoing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, despite how deeply involved you might become with it, and absorbed, and like losing the perception of everything else, it's like, oh, but I forgot that I know that I'm already breathing, that the body is already breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you remember the breathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I like this, how you're saying.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you remember.
[SPEAKER_03]: You remember that you already know you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that unfocuses you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because focusing means losing perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: Focusing means ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_03]: However you spin it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The blurring of the boundaries.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that unfocusing and, like I was saying, you mentioned outlining, confining, you know, unblurring those boundaries, and it's like, that's ānāpānasati, that's satipaṭṭhāna, that's sense-based contemplation, sense-objects, sense-consciousness, sense-content, feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like, all that is the same thing as ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just outlining things, undermining, you know, outlining the domains, undermining the
[SPEAKER_02]: By clarifying it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: The blur is you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how should anyone understand the following instructions in anpanasati?
[SPEAKER_03]: When you are supposed to breathe in long and short.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't that mean that you need to be more involved with the breath?
[SPEAKER_03]: More focused on it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, not more involved, certainly not more focused.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, basically, first, like, if you're able to see clearly enough the intentionality of it, you can then sort of start exercising it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Without losing perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't start immediately by overly intentionally involving yourself with the breath, because you're already... well, the boundaries are already blurred.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to start through knowledge.
[SPEAKER_03]: Knowledge of the breathing, that outlines the knowledge of your intention to breathe.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what I meant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, those are not steps that you just do right off the bat.
[SPEAKER_03]: I read it and I do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: First thing I think of when I read that sutta, that's what that sutta means.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, good luck with that, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that can be said for any sutta, actually.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, no, you... Those are the aspects that you would have worked towards.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you outlined the intentionality of your breathing sufficiently enough, the physicality of your body,
[SPEAKER_03]: If there is the container of anything, any subsequent mind state or intention or whatever, is second to it, within it, then, yes, you can push that intentionality further without blurring the boundaries.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because he still knowingly breathes in long and knowingly breathes out long, knowingly, while breathing in, feels the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Discerns the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Contemplates impermanence.
[SPEAKER_03]: But why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why can't you just feel the body, discern the mind, contemplate impermanence directly?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, you can, but why is this a recommended way?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, eh... the impermanence and the body that you'll be recollecting is your own idea.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's the risk of it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that is rooted in the same, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the cause of that would be the reason why you should be doing ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, still doesn't ask me my question as to why you should be contemplating those things through satipaṭṭhānas, as opposed to just do it yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, okay, so, I think it's about basically balancing, like what you said in the beginning,
[SPEAKER_00]: There's... you can kind of go too far in the direction of always just the body doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now I'm just, like, observing it, kind of, from the outside, almost.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can go too far in the direction of, like, I'm gonna be fully the one doing it, you know, controlling everything, and of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... so it's about, basically, not doing too much of either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not going too much in either direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... so...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you just kind of stay only on the level of knowledge of the breath, which you... is valid, and can already take you quite far, there's a risk of the... there is a risk of the intentionality aspect of it not become... not being clear enough, I would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's just going to be kind of a recollection of something that you're not doing deliberately.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it's not like, it's a kind of, oh yeah, sure, I know about it, but it's not...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, that's what I'm asking, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what are you asking?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what I'm asking is, you can directly contemplate impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can directly contemplate your mind, or you can do it through ānāpānasati, or satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, given the way the Buddha was talking about it, it seems to indicate that it's better to do it through ānāpānasati or through a satipaṭṭhāna
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it makes those contemplations concrete.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's evident enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's better.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that still doesn't explain the difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why are these concrete and these are not so concrete?
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the factor that determines the concreteness of a contemplation?
[SPEAKER_03]: Movement.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the single factor that follows through?
[SPEAKER_03]: We already said it a few times now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're developing it through yonisonmanasikāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because of yonisonmanasikāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: Full stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because yonisonmanasikāra can become something you take for granted.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're developed in it to some extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: And yes, when you attend to things directly,
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, you are attending those things through yoniso manasikāra, to some extent, but not fully, because if you were, well, you would be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, although you already know the principle of yoniso manasikāra inside out, you haven't fully trained in it yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you know?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you're not an arahant yet.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's exactly why ānāpānasati was instructed to sotāpana, sakadāgāmī, anāgāmīs, those who still had some work to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's exactly why they could understand it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, okay, yeah, of course, I absolutely have mastered the knowledge of yoniso manasikāra inside out.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can explain it in hundreds of ways.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, am I an anahant yet?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Means that yoniso manasikāra has not been thoroughly developed.
[SPEAKER_03]: I haven't trained in it sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's exactly what you would do through satipaṭṭhāna and ānāpānasati, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it will prevent you, or it will maintain a degree of that... a necessary degree of that indirectness,
[SPEAKER_03]: Indirectedness to your contemplation of impermanence, to your... through your discerning and communicating with your citta and and so on, that you can overlook or neglect.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, so it anchors it, essentially.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, through recollectiveness, non-forgetfulness of the knowledge of your body breathing here and now, everything that's there, with it, you regard as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the tendency to, if you were to have it, to...
[SPEAKER_03]: But let me now go into those things and really see them as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's overdoing.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's taking away from oneself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, instead of giving in to that tendency to go and overdo it, you stay anchored.
[SPEAKER_03]: You stay with the right reference point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Peripheral knowledge of the body breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And just allow the perception of impermanence in regard to those things to that extent that they are revealed.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to reveal them all.
[SPEAKER_03]: And train in that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same in regard to the feelings, in regard to the state of the animal, the citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to fix it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to change it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, now it's like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again,
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to fix it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to change it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to do anything on account of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that becomes clearer and clearer if you remain anchored.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you remain seeing it indirectly.